Wickham family papers MSS 15753
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
Wickham family papers
1704-circa 1950
Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library
Wickham family
Wickham, John, 1763-1839
Wickham, William Fanning, 1793-1880
Wickham, Lucy Taylor, 1830-1913
Wickham, Williams Carter, 1820-1888
Wickham, Henry Taylor
MSS 15753
9.5 Cubic Feet 19 legal doc boxes, 6 oversize folders.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased from Jerry N. Showalter, on July 3, 2014.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series, Series 1: Business correspondence arranged chronologically (Boxes 1-5). Several business correspondents warranted individual folders based on either the amount of material or the importance of the correspondent. Series 2: Correspondence of John Wickham, arranged alphabetically by the last name of the chief correspondent (Box 5); Series 3: Correspondence of the Wickham and related families, arranged by the last name of the main correspondent (Boxes 6-15); Series 4: Financial and Legal Papers and Miscellany (Boxes 16-19), all arranged in chronological order.
Biographical / Historical
This collection chiefly concerns the Wickham family of Richmond, Virginia and "Hickory Hill" plantation in Hanover County, Virginia, including the families of John Wickham (1763-1839), his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), grandson, Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), and great-grandson, Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943). When other relatives and friends appear in the folder listing, their birth and death dates and relationships are noted if known.
Attorney John Wickham married twice and had two lines of descent. His first wife was Mary Smith Fanning (1775-1799) by whom he had two sons, William Fanning Wickham of "Hickory Hills," married to Anne Butler Carter (1797-1868), and Edmund Fanning Wickham of "Rocky Mount" (1796-1843), married to Anne's sister, Lucy Carter (1799-1835).
After the death of his first wife, John Wickham married Elizabeth Seldon McClurg and had several more children. Some of these children are also represented in these papers.
Scope and Contents
This collection concerns the Wickham family of Richmond, Virginia and "Hickory Hill" plantation in Hanover County, Virginia, including the families of John Wickham (1763-1839), his son, William Fanning Wickham (1793-1880), grandson, Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), and great-grandson, Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943).
The collection contains business correspondence, chiefly concerning legal and agricultural pursuits; family correspondence with immediate and extended relatives; personal correspondence from friends and political associates; two brief diaries discussing the secession and the beginning of the Civil War; financial and legal papers, including lists of books purchased, slave hires, slave purchases, medical care for slaves, losses from invading soldiers during the Civil War, estate values, including slaves, indentures, deeds, receipts, plats and surveys, and lists of slaves by name and age; genealogies and genealogical charts; invitations and calling cards; military papers of General Williams Carter Wickham in Civil War and Captain Williams Carter Wickham, U.S. Navy; news clippings; some notes and manuscripts of William F. Wickham; a few photographs and snapshots; poetry; hand-written recipes; school papers; and sympathy and greeting cards.
Topics include the Civil War, including the relationships between family members in both the North and the South, and attitudes toward secession; many aspects of slavery, often naming the slaves involved; Virginia and national politics; the practice of agriculture in Virginia; the education of the children of Virginia planters, including attendance at the Howard School, Episcopal High School, Washington College and the University of Virginia; military service of General Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888), Captain William Carter Wickham (1887-1985), and other Wickham relatives.
General
Added fa to VH 7 Dec. 2017.
Hickory Hill (Hanover County, Virginia); Plantation life; Slavery--United States -- Virginia; Virginia -- History -- 19th Century; Slaves -- Virginia -- Hanover County; Lee, Robert E., 1807-1870; Mosby, John Singleton, 1833-1916; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852; Wirt, William, 1772-1834; Randolph, John, 1773-1833
- Business correspondence
  - Business Correspondence, 1816-1817; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include:, John Slidell and Co., Thomas C. Keaton, William Lyne, W.P. Mason, W.T. Nivison, William B. Page, Philip Rogers, Thomas Rotch, Penn T. Sale, John M. Shepherd, Peter F. Smith, Thomas Strode, William Sullivan, Thomas Swann, Richard Wallack, Ralph Wingfield, Alice B. Winston, and Zach Vowels
  - Business Correspondence, 1819-1822; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondents, chiefly with Edmund F. Wickham, include: Williams Carter (1819), Archibald Gracie and Robert Gracie (1821), and multiple correspondents in 1822: Curwen and Hagarty, Samuel John Dunlop, King and Gracie, Samuel Lambert, and Robert Hughes and Co.
  - Business Correspondence, 1823 January-February; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: James Dunlop, Ninian Edwards, John Ferguson, C.B. Fleet, William Fleet, Robert Gracie, Francis Gregg, James Hagarty, George E. Harrison, James Henderson, L. Jones, T. Jones, and Robert King.
    Letters involving slavery or slaves include one from L. Jones, asking for protection for "old Billy" and mentioning other issues concerning the welfare of slaves, January 2, 1823, and another letter from Ninian Edwards discussing the possible purchase of a female slave for the wife of Dr. Harvey Lane, January 13, 1823.
  - Business Correspondence, 1823 March-June; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: Henry Arnall, Curwen and Hagarty, [J.] Dunlop, Ninian Edwards, C.B. Fleet, John G. Gamble, Robert G. Harper, George E. Harrison, Jones and Rodes, Hardage Lane, C.C. Lee, Lewis and Tomes, George Marx, John Morgan, and Charles Morris.
    Letters involving slavery include the inquiry by Robert G. Harper, May 5, 182[3], for information about the "present condition, conduct, and prospects" of some manumitted slaves formerly belonging to Samuel Gist and freed in his will and the name and address of some respectable and intelligent person in the area where the freed slaves now live who can send a report to Gist's relatives.
  - Business Correspondence, 1823 July-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondents, chiefly Edmund F. Wickham and William F. Wickham, include: Curwen and Hagarty, James Dunlop, John Dunlop, William Logan Fisher, William Fleet, George Greenhow, George E. Harrison, B.B. Keesee, Robert King, Thomas Kelly, Hardage Lane, Lewis and Tomes, Charles F. Logan, William Lyne, and Robert and John Oliver. One letter mentions a runaway slave named Joe, December 18, 1823.
  - Business Correspondence, 1824 January-July; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: David Barclay, John H. Blair, Carter Braxton, William Burns, William L. Dance, S.W. Dandridge, Aaron Denman, Robert Douthat, Ninian Edwards, William Fleet, Gillingham and Randolphs (G.F. and E. Randolph), James Hagerty, George E. Harrison, John Hopkins, and Thomas and John G. Riddle.
  - Business Correspondence, 1824 August-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: Richard Anderson, John Balfour, Thomas and John S. Biddle, Carter Braxton, William Burns, Hugh Campbell, Robert Douthat, and Gillingham and Randolphs (G.F. and E. Randolph).
  - Business Correspondence, 1827-1828; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: Carter Berkeley, Carter Braxton, Roger Mallory, Thomas Nelson, and William F. Wickham to Thomas B. Coleman. Roger Mallory, the jailor in Petersburg, Virginia, writes concerning a runaway slave named Jim who finally admitted he belonged to William F. Wickham but who had originally claimed to belong to Price Sharpe who was charged with permitting him to "go at large contrary to law," and hire himself out, March 19, 1827.
  - Business Correspondence, 1830 January-June; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: G.H. Bacchus, Thomas T. Bouldin, Thomas B. Coleman, M. Huelin, Benjamin Whitehead Ladd, W.H. McFarland, William Nelson, John W. Payne, William G. Pendleton, M.E.M. Roane, and A.B. Spooner. Topics include the reception of freed slaves in Ohio (Benjamin W. Ladd, March 4, 1830); and the [Samuel?] Gist estate (John M. Payne, April 22, 1830).
  - Business Correspondence, 1830 July-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: Patrick Nesbett Edgar, John Exall, Chapman Johnson, Thomas N. Lee, John Ponsonby Martin, William Nelson, Severn E. Parker, A. Robinson, Jr., William Rowlett, J.S. Skinner, Benjamin Temple, Robert Temple, Thomas Biddle and Company, and John R. Triplett. Topics include: blue wheat (Benjamin and Robert Temple, July 4, 1830 and August 4, 1830); American turf and racing magazine (August 3, 1830; September 1, 1830; October 19, 1830); and a collection of pedigrees for an American Stud Book (October 13, 1830).
  - Business Correspondence, 1832-1839; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: J.D. Andrews, John Corbin, Alfred V. Crenshaw, Crouches & Snead, Gracie & Company, James Gray, Richard B. Haxall, William Hilberg, James Lyle, and Francis Page. Topics include problems with a horse purchased from Wickham (November 15, 1838), the safe arrival of the Andrews family in Houston, Texas (January 28, 1839), and the sending of a slave named Jefferson to fetch two mules from Wickham (April 22, 1839).
  - Business Correspondence, 1842 January-August; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Correspondents, chiefly with William F. Wickham, include: Beers & Poindexter, Robert M. Candlish, John S. Corbin, Robert Ellett, William Linton, A.T.B. Merritt, Nathaniel Nelson, J.W. Pegram, W. Richardson, Thomas Samson, John Shore, John N. Tazewell, James G. Watson, and William L. White. Topics include mention of the horse "Priam" at Merritt's Hicks Ford stud in Virginia and the failure of Wickham's Eclipse mare to foal last spring (May 11, 1842); the dire condition of the [slave?] old Bob Clark and his family on the land of Nathanael Nelson and attempts to provide for their care (June 15 and July 11, 1842); and a discussion of improvements to Wickham's bevel wheel (July 11, 1842) by Thomas Samson of D.J. Burr & Co.
  - Business Correspondence, 1842 September-December; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Correspondents include: John S. Corbin, Nathanael Cross, William Dorbaker, Thomas Ellis and Charles Ellis, Robert G. Gilman, J.H. Martin, [S.H.] Parker, James L. Pendleton, James A. Seddon, Jane J. Swann, George Taylor, John N. Tazewell, William L. White, and John Wight. Topics include lumber needed for a penitentiary and a possible list of slaves written in pencil on an address portion of the letter (October 10, 1842).
  - Business Correspondence, 1844-1847; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondents include: Warwick Barksdale, John Barr, Samuel Cottrell, Richard Gwathmey, John Struthers & Son, Lucius Minor, William Nelson, Lucien B. Price, Richard Randolph, Edmund Ruffin, William D. Taylor, John N. Tazewell, Philip B. Winston, and Richard M. Young (General Land Office). Topics include the sale of two female slaves (January 29, 1845).
  - Business Correspondence, 1848; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondents include: Warwick Barksdale, Wellington Goddin, Phineas Janney, C.C. Lee, Thomas Nelson, Bernard Peyton, [Lucien] B. Price, John T. Rogers, Edmund Ruffin, Robert Taylor, J.R. Underwood, William F. Watson, Joseph Wingfield, and Philip B. Winston. Topics include a description of damage to the property of Joseph Wingfield by the breakage of the mill dam of Wickham (March 12, 1848).
  - Business Correspondence, 1849-1850; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Correspondents include: John Gibson, G.W. Goode, Richard Gwathmey, Benjamin F. Larned (1794-1862), William Leigh, Thomas Nelson, John E. Page, James A. Seddon, Alexander H.H. Stuart, William F. Watson, Hugh A. Watt, W.C. Wickham (to James M. Ford), Edmund Winston, and William Overton Winston. Topics include the shipment of some prairie birds and directions for their care (December 23, 1849); lists of slaves for hire, including "old Fanny," Nancy and her three children, and Betsy (January 1, 1850); request for information about the amount due on account of the division of the Negroes (slaves) (March 5, 1850); William F. Wickham as the guardian of the minor heirs of Robert C. Wickham (April 20, 1850); the offer of the use of a Southdown buck for sheep breeding (July 12, 1850); the increase of visitors to the mountains of Virginia, especially at White Sulphur Springs, the Warm Springs, and the Hot Springs (August 5, 1850); the purchase of stained glass (November 19 and 23, 1850); the return of a wet nurse, "Mamma Betsy" hired the year before for his little boy (July 28, 1849; November 5, 1850); and an opinion about Jenny Lind (December 20, 1850).
  - Business Correspondence, 1853-1861; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include: Alexander Hew, John F. Lay, [Laudonier] J. Randolph; Robert L. Randolph, Allen P. Richardson, William Sayre, William F. Wickham, and Thomas Wight. Topics include the redemption of land in Saline County, Missouri (September 13, 1853) and the settlement with McClurg Wickham, Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham, and John Wickham concerning a loan from John Henry Wickham to them on August 11, 1851 (May 28, 1858).
  - Business Correspondence, 1863-1873; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondents include: J.A. Allen, David Anderson, Jr., A.W. Ball, Ann B. Berkeley, the Reverend P.F. Berkeley, George H. Byrd (Wyman, Byrd and Co. Commission Merchants), [Magrat] Davis, R.B. Davis, Robert Johnston, J.H. Montague, H.C. Parsons, James H. Storrs, John R. Taylor, James Usher, and William F. Wickham (drafts to Ann B. Berkeley, the Reverend P.F. Berkeley, and B.W. Green). Topics include: the question in the legislature concerning the payment of legacies given in Confederate money between 1862-1865 (March 10, 1866); difficulties in settling court cases in West Virginia following the Civil War (November 16, 1866); a request from a woman for legal help in keeping her inheritance in her name and under her control rather than her husband's as her current lawyer advised (April 25, 1867); and reports on the "North Wales" farm (May 20, 27, and 31, 1870).
  - Business Correspondence, 1875-1884; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Correspondents include: James L. Apperson, W.W. Baldwin, Lewis D. Crenshaw, Jr., Isaac Davis, L.R. Dickinson, Maynard Dyson, James S. Earle and Sons, George William Gibson, Charles Herndon, J.M. Hill, I.M. Parr and Son (Commission Merchants), J. Sabin and Sons (Booksellers, Printsellers and Importers), Walter C. Jones, A.C. Loomis, J.H. Montague, Henry Parry, G. Peyton, Joseph T. Priddy, R.H. Maury and Co. (Stock and Exchange Brokers), J.W. Ratcliffe, C.T. Smith, E.D. Starke, A.T. Stewart, W.T. Tinsley, H. Wernich, William F. Wickham (draft to L. Upshur Evans), and Wright and Co., Rio de Janeiro. Topics include: the sale of property in Richmond, Virginia, of a former brewery belonging to the estate of David G. Yuengling, Jr. along the James River called the "James River Steam Brewery" (August 16, 1879).
  - Business Correspondence, undated; 1 folder(s) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Correspondents include: George B. Butler, Alexander Kaslovistsh, and John Watkins.
  - Business Correspondence – John Allison, Petersburg, Virginia, 1824; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence – S. Alvis, 1839-1850; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Alvis discusses the farm operations of the East Tuckahoe Plantation.
  - Business Correspondence – Bevan and Sons, Steam Marble Works, Baltimore, Maryland, 1875; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    The company sends sketches and discusses the replacement of the mantle damaged in the house fire at Hickory Hill.
  - Business Correspondence – Bridges and Snead, Richmond, Virginia, 1833; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Discusses the oak tobacco boxes supplied by Edmund F. Wickham from "Rocky Mills" plantation.
  - Business Correspondence – Dr. Charles Carter (1818-1880), 1867-1873; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Correspondence is chiefly with William F. Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham. Topics include concern about the "military bill" in the South as a way for Congress to get at the landed property there (March 4, 1867); Wickham's fondness for memoirs and other mentions of reading (December 17, 1868; May 30, 1873; June 15 and 20, 1875; February 11, 1876; May 4, 1877; July 2, 1880); and the offer of building supplies currently at "Broad Neck" in order to rebuild the house at "Hickory Hill" after a fire (February 16, 1875).
  - Business Correspondence – Dr. Charles Carter (1818-1888), 1875-1880; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 5a)
    Correspondence is chiefly with William F. Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham. Topics include the financial affairs of their cousin Georgina L. Featherstonhaugh (September 24 and October 28, 1879).
  - Business Correspondence – Hill Carter, 1824-1873; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Topics include Carter's impressions of Bristol College, Bucks County, Pennsylvania (October 18, 1834); complaints about the western states and their impact upon agricultural prices and politics, mentioning James Buchanan by name (July 17, 1846); suggestion that the slaves belonging to their nephews, Robert and John Wickham, be sold to pay the debt of their education (June 18, 1847); mention of a violent snowstorm that occurred just after he had returned home on a gunboat following a period of being nursed by his sister at "Hickory Hill" (November 8, 1862); and the death of Julia Wickham (July 16, 1873).
  - Business Correspondence – Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company, 1871-1873; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Correspondents include C.P. Huntington (President), Henry Taylor Wickham, and Williams C. Wickham and J.S.F. Smith (Paint Creek Depot) concerning the opening of the coal mines on the land purchased from the Hansford heirs and the employment of miners in Kanawha County, West Virginia.
  - Business Correspondence – Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad Company, 1874-1883, 1923-1929; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Business Correspondence - Gater Clarke, 1824; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Business Correspondence - John F. Darby, 1846; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Letters concern lands held by Reuben Jenkins and John Henry Wickham in Saline County, Missouri.
  - Business Correspondence – William Logan Fisher, 1823-1824; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Business Correspondence – Edmund Fontaine, 1849-1850, 1856; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Letters discuss matters concerning the Louisa Railroad, which was chartered by the Virginia General Assembly in 1836, and renamed the Virginia Central Railroad in 1850, with Fontaine as its longtime president.
  - Business Correspondence – H.B. Taliaferro and Co., Tobacco, Grain, Flour, and General Commission Merchants, 1877; 1 folder(s) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Correspondence is concerned with securing payment on the accounts of John Wickham and Littleton W. T. Wickham, brothers of William F. Wickham by an immediate sale of livestock and agricultural goods.
  - Business Correspondence – Philip Haxall (1780-1831), 1830; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Business Correspondence – George Hay (1765-1830), 1823-1824; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Mentions the illness of President Monroe and his own wife, Eliza Kortright Monroe Hay, the daughter of Monroe (August 4, 1823) and expresses disparaging remarks concerning a Yankee business associate (October 19, 1823).
  - Business Correspondence – Reuben Jenkins, 1845-1847; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Business Correspondence – Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849), 1830, 1839-1848; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Topics include a request to help in the administration of the estate of Dr. McClurg (March 2, 1839); fears about the possible death of his son, Thomas, in [Mississippi?] (June 22, 1839); instructions about the purchase of summer clothing for the slaves by Alvis (April 21, 1840); mention that there are 70 slaves associated with the "Rocky Mills" plantation of Edmund Wickham and 40 additional slaves associated with his father's [John Wickham] estate (July 28, 1842). Much of the correspondence in general deals with the settling of the estate of John Wickham (1763-1839).
  - Business Correspondence – James Lyons (1801-1882), 1830-1848; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Business Correspondence – Charles Morris, 1830; 1 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Business Correspondence – Wortham and Magruder, later known as E. and S. Wortham and Co., 4 folders, 1830, 1839-1868; 4 folder(s) (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
  - Business Correspondence – Wortham and Magruder, later known as E. & S. Wortham & Co., 1871-1879; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence of John Wickham (1763-1839)
  - James Breckinridge (1763-1833) to John Wickham, 1824 August 1; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Discusses arrangements for the support of Mr. Harrison's children and his disappointment with Dr. Selden.
  - [Henry Clay?] (1777-1852) to John Wickham, copy, 1836 January 23; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Existence and Location of Originals
    The original letter has been transferred to the Henry Clay Papers.
    Letter of introduction from Henry Clay for Mr. Bainbridge of Kentucky to John Wickham.
  - Joseph Kerr (1765-1837) to John Wickham, 1817 September 29; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Kerr requests copies of any ordinances or laws concerning lands either given or planned to be given by the state of Virginia to the officers and soldiers who served in either the Continental Army or the Virginia state militia for use in the United States Court in Ohio.
  - Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849) to John Wickham, 1833 February 22; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Discusses the best way to secure the claim of Dr. McClurg for surgeon pay during his service in the Continental Army, keeping in mind that the United States will soon find a use for surplus money and mentions Henry Clay as doing a great deal of good [in Congress?].
  - Benjamin Watkins Leigh (1781-1849) to John Wickham, 1836 June 21; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Recommends that they make sure that Dr. [James] McClurg's will is recorded in Kentucky.
  - Judge Peter Lyons (1734-1809) to John Wickham, 1801 March 28; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Notifies Wickham that he has located among his scorched papers enough information to send him a transcript of all he knows or remembers about the bonds of Mr. Balfour and invites him to visit Studley, Virginia.
  - Robert Purviance, Jr. (1779-1858) to John Wickham, 1838 July 12; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Mentions the health concerns of family members and friends in Baltimore, Maryland.
  - Robert Purviance, Jr. (1779-1858) to John Wickham, 1838 August 10; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 9)
    Describes the worsening physical condition of Walter [Maclurg Wickham?] in Baltimore, Maryland.
  - Robert Purviance, Jr. (1779-1858) to John Wickham, 1838 August 13; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Notifies Wickham about the death of Walter [Maclurg Wickham?] in Baltimore, Maryland.
  - Edmund Randolph to John Wickham, 1812 January 14; 1 folder(s) (Box 5, Folder 11)